<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="preface">
  <title>Preface</title>
  <sect1 id="I_sect1_d1e167">
    <title>Audience</title>
    <para>This <indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e172" significance="normal"><primary>analysis</primary><see>code coverage metrics; code quality metrics; tests</see></indexterm><indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e177" significance="normal"><primary>deployment</primary><see>automated deployment; continuous deployment</see></indexterm>book is aimed at relatively technical readers, though no
    prior experience with Continuous Integration is assumed. You may be new to
    Continuous Integration, and would like to learn about the benefits it can
    bring to your development team. Or, you might be using Jenkins or Hudson
    already, and want to discover how you can take your Continuous Integration
    infrastructure further.</para>
    <para>Much of this book discusses Jenkins in the context of Java or
    JVM-based projects. Nevertheless, even if you're using another
    technology stack, this book should give you a good grounding in Continuous
    Integration with Jenkins. We discuss how to build projects using several
    non-Java technologies, including as Grails, Ruby on Rails, and .NET. In
    addition, many topics, such as general configuration, notification,
    distributed builds, and security are applicable no matter what language you're
    using.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="I_sect1_d1e185">
    <title>Book Layout</title>
    <para>Continuous Integration is like a lot of things: the more you put in,
    the more value you'll get out. While even a basic Continuous Integration
    setup will produce positive improvements in your team process, there are
    significant advantages to gradually assimilating and implementing some of
    the more advanced techniques as well. To this end, this book is organized
    as a progressive trek into the world of Continuous Integration with
    Jenkins, going from simple to more advanced. In the first chapter, we
    start off with a sweeping overview of what Jenkins is all about, in the
    form of a high-level guided tour. From there, we progress into how to
    install and configure your Jenkins server and how to set up basic build
    jobs. Once you've mastered the basics, we'll delve into more advanced
    topics, including automated testing practices, security, more advanced
    notification techniques, and measuring and reporting on code quality
    metrics. Next, we move on to more advanced build techniques such as matrix
    builds, distributed builds, and cloud-based CI, before discussing how to
    implement Continuous Deployment with Jenkins. Finally, we cover some tips
    on maintaining your Jenkins server.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="I_sect1_d1e190">
    <title>Jenkins or Hudson?</title>
    <para>As we <indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e195" significance="normal"><primary>Jenkins</primary><secondary>history of</secondary></indexterm><indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e200" significance="normal"><primary>Hudson</primary></indexterm>mention in the introduction, Jenkins was originally, and up
    until recently, known as Hudson. In 2009, Oracle purchased Sun and
    inherited the Hudson code base. In early 2011, tensions between Oracle
    and the open source community reached rupture point and the project forked
    into two separate entities: Jenkins, run by most of the original Hudson
    developers, and Hudson, which remained under the control of Oracle.</para>
    <para>As the title suggests, this book is primarily focused on Jenkins.
    However, much of the book was initially written before the fork, and the
    products remain very similar. So, although the examples and illustrations
    do usually refer to Jenkins, almost all of what's discussed will also
    apply to Hudson.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="preface-sect-fontConventions">
    <title>Font Conventions</title>
    <para>This <indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e211" significance="normal"><primary>fonts used in this book</primary></indexterm><indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e214" significance="normal"><primary>conventions used in this book</primary></indexterm>book follows certain conventions for font usage.
    Understanding these conventions up-front makes it easier to use this
    book.</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Italic</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Used for filenames, file extensions, URLs, application names,
          emphasis, and new terms when they're first introduced.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <literal moreinfo="none">Constant width</literal>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Used for Java class names, methods, variables, properties,
          data types, database elements, and snippets of code that appear in
          text.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <userinput moreinfo="none">Constant width bold</userinput>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Used for commands you enter at the command line and to
          highlight new code inserted in a running example.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <replaceable>Constant width italic</replaceable>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Used to annotate output.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="I_sect1_d1e246">
    <title>Command-Line Conventions</title>
    <para>From time to time, this book discusses command-line instructions.
    When we do, output produced by the console (e.g., command prompts or
    screen output) is displayed in normal characters, and commands (what you
    type) are written in <userinput moreinfo="none">bold</userinput>. For example:</para>
    <screen format="linespecific">$ <userinput moreinfo="none">ls -al</userinput>
total 168
drwxr-xr-x   16 johnsmart  staff    544 21 Jan 07:20 .
drwxr-xr-x+  85 johnsmart  staff   2890 21 Jan 07:10 ..
-rw-r--r--    1 johnsmart  staff     30 26 May  2009 .owner
-rw-r--r--@   1 johnsmart  staff   1813 16 Apr  2009 config.xml
drwxr-xr-x  181 johnsmart  staff   6154 26 May  2009 fingerprints
drwxr-xr-x   17 johnsmart  staff    578 16 Apr  2009 jobs
drwxr-xr-x    3 johnsmart  staff    102 15 Apr  2009 log
drwxr-xr-x   63 johnsmart  staff   2142 26 May  2009 plugins
-rw-r--r--    1 johnsmart  staff     46 26 May  2009 queue.xml
-rw-r--r--@   1 johnsmart  staff     64 13 Nov  2008 secret.key
-rw-r--r--    1 johnsmart  staff  51568 26 May  2009 update-center.json
drwxr-xr-x    3 johnsmart  staff    102 26 May  2009 updates
drwxr-xr-x    3 johnsmart  staff    102 15 Apr  2009 userContent
drwxr-xr-x   12 johnsmart  staff    408 17 Feb  2009 users
drwxr-xr-x   28 johnsmart  staff    952 26 May  2009 war</screen>
    <para>Where necessary, the backslash character at the end of the line is
    used to indicate a line break: you can type this all on one line (without
    the backslash) if you prefer. Don’t forget to ignore the “&gt;” character
    at the start of the subsequent lines—it’s a Unix prompt character:</para>
    <screen format="linespecific">$ wget -O - http://jenkins-ci.org/debian/jenkins-ci.org.key \
&gt; | sudo apt-key add -</screen>
    <para>For consistency, unless we're discussing a Windows-specific issue,
    we'll use Unix-style command prompts (the dollar sign, “$”), as shown
    here:</para>
    <screen format="linespecific">$ java -jar jenkins.war</screen>
    <para>or:</para>
    <screen format="linespecific">$ svn list svn://localhost</screen>
    <para>However, unless we say otherwise, Windows users can safely use these
    commands from the Windows command console:</para>
    <screen format="linespecific">C:\Documents and Settings\Owner&gt; java -jar jenkins.war</screen>
    <para>or:</para>
    <screen format="linespecific">C:\Documents and Settings\Owner&gt; svn list svn://localhost</screen>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="I_sect1_d1e280">
    <title>Contributors</title>
    <para>This <indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e285" significance="normal"><primary>contributors for this book</primary></indexterm>book was not written alone. Rather, it's been a
    collaborative effort involving many people playing different roles. In
    particular, the following people generously contributed their time,
    knowledge, and writing skill to make this a better book:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Evgeny Goldin</emphasis> is<indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e295" significance="normal"><primary>Goldin, Evgeny (contributor)</primary></indexterm> a Russian-born software engineer living in Israel. He's
        a lead developer at Thomson Reuters where he’s responsible for a
        number of activities, some of which are directly related to Maven,
        Groovy, and build tools such as Artifactory and Jenkins. He has vast
        experience in a range of technologies, including Perl, Java,
        JavaScript, and Groovy. Build tools and dynamic languages are Evgeny’s
        favorite subjects about which he often writes, presents, or blogs.
        These days he writes for GroovyMag, Methods &amp; Tools, and runs
        two open source projects of his own: <ulink url="http://evgeny-goldin.com/wiki/Maven-plugins">Maven-plugins</ulink>
        and <ulink url="http://evgeny-goldin.com/wiki/GCommons">GCommons</ulink>. He
        blogs at <ulink url="http://evgeny-goldin.com/blog"/> and can
        be found on Twitter as <emphasis>@evgeny_goldin</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>Evgeny contributed a section on generating your Maven build jobs
        automatically in <xref linkend="chapter-advanced-builds"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Matthew McCullough</emphasis> <indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e319" significance="normal"><primary>McCullough, Matthew (contributor)</primary></indexterm>is an energetic 15 year veteran of enterprise software
        development, open source education, and co-founder of Ambient Ideas,
        LLC, a Denver consultancy. Matthew currently is a trainer for
        GitHub.com, author of the Git Master Class series for O’Reilly,
        speaker at over 30 national and international conferences, author of 3
        of the top 10 DZone RefCards, and President of the Denver Open Source
        Users Group. His current topics of research center around project
        automation: build tools (Maven, Leiningen, Gradle), distributed
        version control (Git), Continuous Integration (Jenkins), and Quality
        Metrics (Sonar). Matthew resides in Denver, Colorado with his
        beautiful wife and two young daughters, who are active in nearly every
        outdoor activity Colorado has to offer.</para>
        <para>Matthew wrote the section on integrating Git with Jenkins in
        <xref linkend="chapter-build-jobs"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Juven Xu</emphasis> is <indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e332" significance="normal"><primary>Xu, Juven (contributor)</primary></indexterm>a software engineer from China who works for Sonatype.
        An active member of the open source community and recognized Maven
        expert, Juven was responsible for the Chinese translation of
        <emphasis>Maven: The Definitive Guide</emphasis> as well as an
        original Chinese reference book on Maven. He's also currently working
        on the Chinese translation of the present book.</para>
        <para>Juven wrote the section on IRC notifications in <xref linkend="chapter-notification"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Rene Groeschke</emphasis> is<indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e348" significance="normal"><primary>Groeschke, Rene (contributor)</primary></indexterm> a software engineer at Cassidian Systems, formerly
        known as EADS Deutschland GmbH, as well as an open source enthusiast.
        A certified ScrumMaster with about 7 years experience as a programmer
        in several enterprise Java projects, he's especially focused on Agile
        methodologies like Continuous Integration and Test-Driven Development.
        Besides his daily business, the University of Corporate Education in
        Friedrichshafen allows him to spread the word about scrum and scrum
        related topics by giving lectures to the bachelor-level students of
        information technology.</para>
        <para>Rene contributed the section on building projects with Gradle in
        <xref linkend="chapter-build-jobs"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="I_sect1_d1e356">
    <title>The Review Team</title>
    <para>The technical review process for this book was a little different than
    the approach taken for most books. Rather than having one or two technical
    reviewers read the entire book near the end of the book writing process, a
    team of volunteers from the Jenkins community, including many key Jenkins
    developers, were able to read chapters as they were written. This review
    team was made up of the following people: Alan Harder, Andrew Bayer, Carlo
    Bonamico, Chris Graham, Eric Smalling, Gregory Boissinot, Harald <phrase role="keep-together">Soevik</phrase>, Julien Simpson, Juven Xu, Kohsuke
    Kawaguchi, Martijn Verburg, Ross Rowe, and Tyler Ballance.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="I_sect1_d1e364">
    <title>Book Sponsors</title>
    <para>This <indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e369" significance="normal"><primary>sponsors for this book</primary></indexterm>book would not have been possible without the help of
    several organizations who were willing to assist with and fund the
    book-writing process.</para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Wakaleo Consulting</title>
      <para><ulink url="http://www.wakaleo.com">Wakaleo Consulting</ulink>
      <indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e380" significance="normal"><primary>Wakaleo Consulting (sponsor)</primary></indexterm>is a consulting company that helps organizations optimize
      their software development process. Lead by John Ferguson Smart, author
      of this book and <ulink url="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596527938"><emphasis>Java Power
      Tools</emphasis></ulink>, Wakaleo Consulting provides consulting,
      training and mentoring services in Agile Java Development and Testing
      Practices, Software Development Life Cycle optimization, and Agile
      Methodologies.</para>
      <para>Wakaleo helps companies with training and assistance in areas such
      as Continuous Integration, Build Automation, Test-Driven Development,
      Automated Web Testing, and Clean Code, using open source tools such as
      Maven, Jenkins, Selenium 2, and Nexus. Wakaleo Consulting also runs
      public and on-site training around Continuous Integration and Continuous
      Deployment, Build Automation, Clean Code practices, Test-Driven
      Development, and Behavior-Driven Development, including Certified Scrum
      Developer (CSD) courses.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>CloudBees</title>
      <para><ulink url="http://www.cloudbees.com">CloudBees</ulink> <indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e397" significance="normal"><primary>CloudBees (sponsor)</primary></indexterm>is the only cloud company focused on servicing the
      complete develop-to-deploy life cycle of Java web applications in the
      cloud. The company is also the world’s premier expert on the
      Jenkins/Hudson Continuous Integration tool.</para>
      <para>Jenkins/Hudson creator Kohsuke Kawaguchi leads a CloudBees team of
      experts from around the world. They’ve created Nectar, a supported and
      enhanced version of Jenkins that's available on-premise by
      subscription. If you depend on Jenkins for mission-critical software
      processes, Nectar provides a highly-tested, stable, and fully-supported
      version of Jenkins. It also includes Nectar-only functionality such as
      automatic scaling to VMware virtual machines.</para>
      <para>If you’re ready to explore the power of Continuous Integration in
      the cloud, CloudBees makes Jenkins/Hudson available as part of its
      DEV@cloud build platform. You can get started with Jenkins instantly and
      can scale as needed—no big up-front investment in build servers, no more
      limited capacity for builds, and no maintenance hassles. Once an
      application is ready to go live, you can deploy on CloudBees’s RUN@cloud
      Platform as a Service in just a few clicks.</para>
      <para>With CloudBees’s DEV@cloud and RUN@cloud services, you don’t have
      to worry about servers, virtual machines, or IT staff. And with Nectar,
      you enjoy the most powerful, stable, supported Jenkins available.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Odd-e</title>
      <para><ulink url="http://www.odd-e.com">Odd-e</ulink> is<indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e414" significance="normal"><primary>Odd-e (sponsor)</primary></indexterm> an Asian-based company that builds products in innovative
      ways and helps others achieve the same. The team consists of experienced
      coaches and product developers who work according to the values of
      scrum, agile, lean, and craftsmanship, and the company is structured the
      same way. For example, Odd-e doesn’t have an organizational hierarchy or
      managers making decisions for others. Instead, individuals self-organize
      and use all their skills to continuously improve their competence. The
      company provides training and follow-up coaching to help others
      collaboratively seek and develop a better way of working.</para>
      <para>It's not the job but the values that bind Odd-e together. Its
      members love building software, value learning and contribution over
      maximizing profit, and are committed to supporting open source
      development in Asia.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="I_sect1_d1e420">
    <title>Using Code Examples</title>
    <para>This <indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e425" significance="normal"><primary>code examples, using</primary></indexterm>book is an open source book, published under the Creative
    Commons License. The book was written in DocBook, using XmlMind. The
    book’s source code can be found on GitHub at <ulink url="http://github.com/wakaleo/jenkins-the-definitive-guide-book"/>.</para>
    <para>The sample Jenkins projects used in this book are open source and
    freely available online—see the book’s web page at <ulink url="http://www.wakaleo.com/books/jenkins-the-definitive-guide"/>
    for more details.</para>
    <para>This book is here to help you get your job done. In general, you may
    use the code in this book in your programs and documentation. You don't
    need to contact us for permission unless you’re reproducing a significant
    portion of the code. For example, writing a program that uses several
    chunks of code from this book doesn't require permission. Selling or
    distributing a CD-ROM of examples from O’Reilly books does require
    permission. Answering a question by citing this book and quoting example
    code doesn't require permission. Incorporating a significant amount of
    example code from this book into your product’s documentation does require
    permission.</para>
    <para>We appreciate, but do not require, attribution. An attribution
    usually includes the <phrase role="keep-together">title, author,</phrase>
    publisher, and ISBN. For example: “<emphasis>Jenkins: The Definitive
    Guide</emphasis> by John <phrase>Ferguson</phrase> Smart (O’Reilly).
    Copyright 2011 John Ferguson Smart, 978-1-449-30535-2.”</para>
    <para>If you feel your use of code examples falls outside fair use or the
    permission given above, feel free to contact us at
    <email>permissions@oreilly.com</email>.</para>
  </sect1>
  <?dbfo-need height=”1in”?>
  <sect1 id="I_sect1_d1e455">
    <title>Safari® Books Online</title>
    <note role="safarienabled">
      <para>Safari Books Online is an on-demand digital library that lets you
      easily search over 7,500 technology and creative reference books and
      videos to find the answers you need quickly.</para>
    </note>
    <para>With a subscription, you can read any page and watch any video from
    our library online. Read books on your cell phone and mobile devices.
    Access new titles before they're available for print, and get exclusive
    access to manuscripts in development and post feedback for the authors.
    Copy and paste code samples, organize your favorites, download chapters,
    bookmark key sections, create notes, print out pages, and benefit from
    tons of other time-saving features.</para>
    <para>O’Reilly Media has uploaded this book to the Safari Books Online
    service. To have full digital access to this book and others on similar
    topics from O’Reilly and other publishers, sign up for free at <ulink role="orm:hideurl:ital" url="http://my.safaribooksonline.com/?portal=oreilly">http://my.safaribooksonline.com</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="I_sect1_d1e468">
    <title>How to Contact Us</title>
    <para>Please <indexterm id="I_indexterm_d1e473" significance="normal"><primary>contact information for this book</primary></indexterm>address comments and questions concerning this book to the
    publisher:</para>
    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member>O’Reilly Media, Inc.</member>
      <member>1005 Gravenstein Highway North</member>
      <member>Sebastopol, CA 95472</member>
      <member>800-998-9938 (in the United States or Canada)</member>
      <member>707-829-0515 (international or local)</member>
      <member>707-829-0104 (fax)</member>
    </simplelist>
    <para>We have a web page for this book, where we list errata, examples,
    and any additional information. You can access this page at:</para>
    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member>
        <ulink url="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/9781449305352"/>
      </member>
    </simplelist>
    <para>To comment or ask technical questions about this book, send email
    to:</para>
    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member>
        <email>bookquestions@oreilly.com</email>
      </member>
    </simplelist>
    <para>For more information about our books, courses, conferences, and
    news, see our website at <ulink url="http://www.oreilly.com"/>.</para>
    <para>Find us on Facebook: <ulink url="http://facebook.com/oreilly"/></para>
    <para>Follow us on Twitter: <ulink url="http://twitter.com/oreillymedia"/></para>
    <para>Watch us on YouTube: <ulink url="http://www.youtube.com/oreillymedia"/></para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="I_sect1_d1e514">
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    <para>First and foremost, my wonderful wife, Chantal, and boys, James and
    William, without whose love, support, and tolerance this book would not
    have been possible.</para>
    <para>I'd like to thank Mike Loukides for working with me once again
    on this book project, and the whole O’Reilly team for their high standards
    of work.</para>
    <para>Thank you to Kohsuke Kawaguchi for having created Jenkins, and for
    still being the driving force behind this brilliant product. Thanks also
    to Francois Dechery, Sacha Labourey, Harpreet Singh, and the rest of the
    CloudBees team for their help and support.</para>
    <para>I'm also very grateful to those who took the time and energy to
    contribute work to the book: Evgeny Goldin, Matthew McCullough, Juven Xu,
    and Rene Groeschke.</para>
    <para>A great thanks goes out to the following reviewers who provided
    valuable feedback throughout the whole writing process: Alan Harder,
    Andrew Bayer, Carlo Bonamico, Chris Graham, Eric Smalling, Gregory
    Boissinot, Harald Soevik, Julien Simpson, Juven Xu, Kohsuke Kawaguchi,
    Martijn Verburg, Ross Rowe, and Tyler Ballance.</para>
    <para>Thank you to Andrew Bayer, Martijn Verburg, Matthew McCullough, Rob
    Purcell, Ray King, Andrew Walker, and many others, whose discussions and
    feedback provided me with inspiration and the ideas that made this book
    what it is.</para>
    <para>Many other people have helped in various ways to make this book
    much richer and more complete than it would have been otherwise: Geoff and
    Alex Bullen, Pete Thomas, Gordon Weir, Jay Zimmerman, Tim O’Brien, Russ
    Miles, Richard Paul, Julien Simpson, John Stevenson, Michael Neale, Arnaud
    Héritier, and Manfred Moser.</para>
    <para>And finally, a great thank you to the Hudson/Jenkins developer and
    user communities for their ongoing encouragement and support.</para>
  </sect1>
</preface>
