<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="copyright" role="copyrightpg">
  <title>Copyright</title>

  <para>Copyright © ${copyright.year} ${book.principle.author}</para>

  <para>Printed version published by ${publisher.name},
  ${publisher.address}.</para>

  <para>Online version published by ${project.organization.name},
  ${organization.address}.</para>

  <para>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons
  Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivative Works 3.0 United States license. For
  more information about this license, see <ulink
  url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/us/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/us/</ulink>.
  You are free to share, copy, distribute, display, and perform the work under
  the following conditions:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>You must attribute the work to ${book.principle.author}</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>You may not use this work for commercial purposes.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>You may not alter, transform, or build upon this work.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Java™ and all Java-based trademarks and logos are trademarks or
  registered trademarks of Sun Microsystems, Inc., in the United States and
  other countries.</para>

  <para>Eclipse™ is a trademark of the Eclipse Foundation, Inc., in the United
  States and other countries.</para>

  <para>Apache and the Apache feather logo are trademarks of The Apache
  Software Foundation.</para>

  <para>Linux® is the registered trademark of Linus Torvalds in the U.S. and
  other countries.</para>

  <para>Many of the designations used by manufacturers and sellers to
  distinguish their products are claimed as trademarks. Where those
  designations appear in this book, and ${project.organization.name} was aware
  of a trademark claim, the designations have been printed in caps or initial
  caps.</para>

  <para>While every precaution has been taken in the preparation of this book,
  the publisher and authors assume no responsibility for errors or omissions,
  or for damages resulting from the use of the information contained
  herein.</para>
</preface>
