<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="preface">
  <title>Preface</title>

  <section>
    <title>Audience</title>

    <para>This book is aimed at at relatively technical readers, though no
    prior experience with Continuous Integration is assumed. You may be new to
    Continuous Integration, and would like to learn about the benefits it can
    bring to your development team. Or, you might be using Jenkins or Hudson
    already, and want to discover how you can take your Continuous Integration
    infrastructure further.</para>

    <para>Much of the book discusses Jenkins in the context of Java or
    JVM-related projects. Nevertheless, even if you are using another
    technology stack, this book should give you a good grounding in Continuous
    Integration with Jenkins. We discuss how to build projects using several
    non-Java technologies, including as Grails, Ruby on Rails and .NET. In
    addition, many topics, such as general configuration, notification,
    distributed builds and security are applicable no matter what language you
    are using.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Book layout</title>

    <para>Continuous Integration is like a lot of things: the more you put in,
    the more value you will get out. While even a  basic Continuous
    Integration setup will produce positive improvements in your team process,
    there are significant advantages to gradually assimilating and
    implementing some of the more advanced techniques as well. To this end,
    this book is organized as a progressive trek into the world of Continuous
    Integration with Jenkins, going from simple to more advanced. In the first
    chapter, we start off with a sweeping overview of what Jenkins is all
    about, in the form of a high level guided tour. From there, we progress
    into how to install and configure your Jenkins server and how to set up
    basic build jobs. Once we have mastered the basics, we will delve into
    more advanced topics, including automated testing practices, security,
    more advanced notification techniques, and measuring and reporting on code
    quality metrics. Next, we move on to more advanced build techniques such
    as matrix builds, distributed builds and cloud-based CI, before discussing
    how to implement Continuous Deployment with Jenkins. Finally, we cover
    some tips on maintaining your Jenkins server.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Jenkins or Hudson?</title>

    <para>As we discuss in the introduction, Jenkins was originally, and up
    until recently, known as Hudson. In 2009, Oracle purchased Sun and
    inherited the code base of Hudson. In early 2011, tensions between Oracle
    and the open source community reached rupture point and the project forked
    into two separate entities: Jenkins, run by most of the original Hudson
    developers, and Hudson, which remained under the control of Oracle.</para>

    <para>As the title suggests, this book is primarily focused on Jenkins.
    However, much of the book was initially written before the fork, and the
    products remain very similar. So, although the examples and illustrations
    do usually refer to Jenkins, almost all of what is discussed will also
    apply to Hudson.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="preface-sect-fontConventions">
    <title>Font Conventions</title>

    <para>This book follows certain conventions for font usage. Understanding
    these conventions up-front makes it easier to use this book.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="italic">Italic</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for filenames, file extensions, URLs, application names,
          emphasis, and new terms when they are first introduced.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal moreinfo="none">Constant width</literal></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for Java class names, methods, variables, properties,
          data types, database elements, and snippets of code that appear in
          text.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold"> <literal moreinfo="none">Constant width
        bold</literal> </emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for commands you enter at the command line and to
          highlight new code inserted in a running example.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="italic"> <literal moreinfo="none">Constant width
        italic</literal> </emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used to annotate output.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Command-line conventions</title>

    <para>From time to time, this book discusses command-line instructions.
    When we do, output produced by the console (e.g. command prompts or screen
    output) is displayed in normal characters, and commands (what you type)
    are written in <command>bold</command>. For example: <screen>$ <command>ls -al</command>
total 168
drwxr-xr-x   16 johnsmart  staff    544 21 Jan 07:20 .
drwxr-xr-x+  85 johnsmart  staff   2890 21 Jan 07:10 ..
-rw-r--r--    1 johnsmart  staff     30 26 May  2009 .owner
-rw-r--r--@   1 johnsmart  staff   1813 16 Apr  2009 config.xml
drwxr-xr-x  181 johnsmart  staff   6154 26 May  2009 fingerprints
drwxr-xr-x   17 johnsmart  staff    578 16 Apr  2009 jobs
drwxr-xr-x    3 johnsmart  staff    102 15 Apr  2009 log
drwxr-xr-x   63 johnsmart  staff   2142 26 May  2009 plugins
-rw-r--r--    1 johnsmart  staff     46 26 May  2009 queue.xml
-rw-r--r--@   1 johnsmart  staff     64 13 Nov  2008 secret.key
-rw-r--r--    1 johnsmart  staff  51568 26 May  2009 update-center.json
drwxr-xr-x    3 johnsmart  staff    102 26 May  2009 updates
drwxr-xr-x    3 johnsmart  staff    102 15 Apr  2009 userContent
drwxr-xr-x   12 johnsmart  staff    408 17 Feb  2009 users
drwxr-xr-x   28 johnsmart  staff    952 26 May  2009 war</screen></para>

    <para>Where necessary, the backslash character at the end of the line is
    used to indicate a line-break: you can type this all on one line (without
    the backslash) if you prefer. Don't forget to ignore the '&gt;' character
    at the start of the subsequent lines - it's a unix prompt
    character:<screen>$ <command>wget -O - http://jenkins-ci.org/debian/jenkins-ci.org.key \
</command>&gt; <command>| sudo apt-key add -</command></screen>For
    consistency, unless we are discussing a Windows-specific issue, we will
    use Unix-style command prompts (the dollar sign, '$'), as shown
    here:</para>

    <para><screen>$ <command>java -jar jenkins.war</command></screen></para>

    <para>or</para>

    <para><screen>$ <command>svn list svn://localhost</command></screen></para>

    <para>However, unless we say otherwise, Windows users can safely use these
    commands from the Windows command console:<screen>C:\Documents and Settings\Owner&gt; <command>java -jar jenkins.war</command></screen></para>

    <para>or</para>

    <screen>C:\Documents and Settings\Owner&gt; <command>svn list svn://localhost</command></screen>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Contributors</title>

    <para>This book was not written alone. Rather, it has been a collaborative
    effort involving many people playing different roles. In particular, the
    following people generously contributed their time, knowledge and writing
    skill to make this a better book:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><command>Evgeny Goldin</command> is a Russian-born software
        engineer living in Israel. He is a lead developer at Thomson Reuters
        where he's responsible for a number of activities, some of which are
        directly related to Maven, Groovy and build tools such as Artifactory
        and Jenkins. He has a vast experience in a range of technologies,
        including Perl, Java, JavaScript and Groovy. Build tools and dynamic
        languages are Evgeny's favorite subjects about which he often writes,
        presents or blogs. These days he is writing for GroovyMag, Methods
        &amp; Tools and runs two open-source projects of his own:
        "Maven-plugins" (evgeny-goldin.com/wiki/Maven-plugins) and "GCommons"
        (evgeny-goldin.com/wiki/GCommons). He blogs at
        http://evgeny-goldin.com/blog and can be found on Twitter as
        @evgeny_goldin.</para>

        <para>Evgeny contributed a section on generating your Maven build jobs
        automatically in the Advanced Builds chapter.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>Matthew McCullough</command> is an energetic 15 year
        veteran of enterprise software development, open source education, and
        co-founder of Ambient Ideas, LLC, a Denver consultancy. Matthew
        currently is a trainer for GitHub.com, author of the Git Master Class
        series for O'Reilly, speaker at over 30 national and international
        conferences, author of three of the top 10 DZone RefCards, and
        President of the Denver Open Source Users Group. His current topics of
        research center around project automation: build tools (Maven,
        Leiningen, Gradle), distributed version control (Git), Continuous
        Integration (Jenkins) and Quality Metrics (Sonar). Matthew resides in
        Denver, Colorado with his beautiful wife and two young daughters, who
        are active in nearly every outdoor activity Colorado has to
        offer.</para>

        <para>Matthew wrote the section on integrating Git with
        Jenkins.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>Juven Xu</command> is a software engineer from China
        who works for Sonatype. An active member of the Open Source community
        and recognized Maven expert, Juven was responsible for the Chinese
        translation of 'Maven: The Definitive Guide' as well as an original
        Chinese reference book on Maven. He is also currently working on the
        Chinese translation of the present book.</para>

        <para>Juven wrote the section on IRC notifications.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>Rene Groeschke</command> is a software engineer at
        Cassidian Systems, formerly known as EADS Deutschland GmbH, as well as
        an Open Source enthusiast. A certified ScrumMaster with about 7 years
        experience as a programmer in several enterprise java projects, he is
        especially focused on agile methodologies like continuous integration
        and test driven development. Besides his daily business, the
        university of coorporate education in Friedrichshafen allows him to
        spread the word about scrum and scrum related topics by giving
        lectures for the bachelor students of information technology.</para>

        <para>Rene contributed the section on building projects with
        Gradle.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The review team</title>

    <para>The technical review process for this book was a little different to
    the approach taken for most books. Rather than having one or two technical
    reviewers read the entire book near the end of the book-writing process, a
    team of volunteers from the Jenkins community, including many key Jenkins
    developers, were able to read chapters as they were written. This review
    team was made up of the following people: Alan Harder, Andrew Bayer, Carlo
    Bonamico, Chris Graham, Eric Smalling, Gregory Boissinot, Harald Soevik,
    Julien Simpson, Juven Xu, Kohsuke Kawaguchi, Martijn Verberg, Ross Rowe
    and Tyler Ballance.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Book Sponsors</title>

    <para>This book would not have been possible without the help of several
    organizations who were willing to assist with and fund the book-writing
    process.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Platinum Sponsors</title>

      <section>
        <title>Wakaleo Consulting</title>

        <para>Wakaleo Consulting (<uri>http:/www.wakaleo.com</uri>) is a
        consulting company that helps organisations optimize their software
        development process. Lead by John Ferguson Smart, author of 'Java
        Power Tools' and the present book, Wakaleo Consulting provides
        consulting, training and mentoring services in Agile Java Development
        and Testing Practices, Software Development Life Cycle optimization
        and Agile Methodologies.</para>

        <para>Wakaleo helps companies with training and assistance in areas
        such as Continuous Integration, Build Automation, Test-Driven
        Development, Automated Web Testing and Clean Code, using open source
        tools such as Maven, Jenkins, Selenium 2, and Nexus. Wakaleo
        Consulting also runs public and on-site training around Continuous
        Integration and Continuous Deployment, Build Automation, Clean Code
        practices, Test Driven Development and Behaviour Driven Development,
        including Certified Scrum Developer (CSD) courses.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Cloudbees</title>

        <para>CloudBees (<uri>http://www.cloudbees.com</uri>) is the only
        cloud company focused on servicing the complete develop-to-deploy
        lifecycle of Java web applications in the cloud. The company is also
        the world’s premier expert on the Jenkins/Hudson continuous
        integration tool.</para>

        <para>Jenkins/Hudson creator Kohsuke Kawaguchi leads a CloudBees team
        of experts from around the world. They’ve created Nectar, a supported
        and enhanced version of Jenkins that is available on-premise by
        subscription. If you depend on Jenkins for mission-critical software
        processes, Nectar provides a highly-tested, stable, and
        fully-supported version of Jenkins. It also includes Nectar-only
        functionality such as automatic scaling to VMWare virtual
        machines.</para>

        <para>If you’re ready to explore the power of continuous integration
        in the cloud, CloudBees makes Jenkins/Hudson available as part of its
        DEV@cloud build platform. You can get started with Jenkins instantly
        and can scale as needed – no big up-front investment in build servers,
        no more limited capacity for builds, and no maintenance hassles. Once
        an application is ready to go live, you can deploy on CloudBees’
        RUN@cloud Platform as a Service in just a few clicks.</para>

        <para>With CloudBees’ DEV@cloud and RUN@cloud services, you don’t have
        to worry about servers, virtual machines or IT staff. And with Nectar,
        you enjoy the most powerful, stable, supported Jenkins
        available.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Gold Sponsors</title>

      <section>
        <title>Odd-e</title>

        <para>Odd-e (<uri>http://www.odd-e.com</uri>) is a small company based
        in Singapore focusing on software quality, agile and lean development,
        training and coaching.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>

    <para>First and foremost, my wonderful wife Chantal and boys James and
    William, without whose love, support and tolerance this book would not
    have been possible.</para>

    <para>I would like to thank Mike Loukides for working with me once again
    on this book project, and the whole O'Reilly team for their high standards
    of work.</para>

    <para>Thank you Kohsuke Kawaguchi for having created Jenkins, and who is
    still the driving force behind this brilliant product. Thanks also to
    Francois Dechery, Sacha Labourey and the rest of the Cloudbees team for
    their help and support. </para>

    <para>I am also very grateful to those who took the time and energy to
    contribute work to the book: Evgeny Goldin, Matthew McCullough, Juven Xu,
    and Rene Groeschke.</para>

    <para>A great thanks goes out to the following reviewers, who provided
    valuable feedback throughout the whole writing process: Alan Harder,
    Andrew Bayer, Carlo Bonamico, Chris Graham, Eric Smalling, Gregory
    Boissinot, Harald Soevik, Julien Simpson, Juven Xu, Kohsuke Kawaguchi,
    Martijn Verberg, Ross Rowe and Tyler Ballance. </para>

    <para>Thank you Andrew Bayer, Martijn Verburg, Matthew McCullough, Rob
    Purcell, Ray King, Andrew Walker and many others, whose discussions and
    feedback provided me with inspiration and the ideas that made this book
    what it is.</para>

    <para>And many other people have helped in various ways to make this book
    much richer and more complete than it would have been otherwise: Geoff and
    Alex Bullen, Pete Thomas, Gordon Weir, Jay Zimmerman, Tim O'Brien, Russ
    Miles, Richard Paul, Julien Simpson, John Stevenson, Michael Neale, Arnaud
    Héritier, and Manfred Moser.</para>

    <para>And finally a great thank you to the Hudson/Jenkins developer and
    user community for the ongoing encouragement and support.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Code samples</title>

    <para>The sample Jenkins projects used in this book are open source and
    freely available online - see the book's web page at
    <uri>http://www.wakaleo.com/books/jenkins-the-definitive-guide</uri> for
    more details.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Online version and source code</title>

    <para>This book is an open source book, published under the Creative
    Commons License. The book was written in Docbook, using XmlMind. The
    book's source code can be found on Github at
    <uri>http://www.github.org/wakaleo/jenkins-the-definitive-guide</uri>.</para>
  </section>
</preface>
